Guide to the Pennsylvania Commission for Women Records, 1979-1988 AIS.2006.10
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pennsylvania Commission for Women Records
1979-1988
1983-1987
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pennsylvania. Commission for Women
AIS.2006.10
2.25 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
The Pennsylvania Commission for Women (PACW) was established in 1975 by Executive Order 1975-3 to insure that women had full and equal opportunities as citizens of the Commonwealth and to be a strong advocate for the rights of women in the state. Their records highlight efforts to eradicate sex discrimination, raise awareness and educate the public on issues concerning women in Pennsylvania.
History
The Pennsylvania Commission for Women (PACW) was created by Executive Order 1975-3 and signed by Governor Milton J. Shapp on February 27, 1975. The Commission's objective was to develop and carry out policies "to help insure that women had full and equal opportunities as citizens of the Commonwealth and to increase State government's effort to eradicate sex discrimination against women in Pennsylvania." The Commission was also tasked with being a strong advocate for the rights of women, to raise awareness, and to educate the public on issues concerning women.
The PACW was comprised of "at least fifteen but not more than twenty-one members appointed by the Governor and shall function in an advisory capacity to the Director." Members served one or two year terms and served without salary. The commission director was appointed by the Governor and reported directly to him, advising on matters affecting women.
To raise awareness for and to educate the public on issues concerning women, the Commission would regularly give speeches to groups such as the League of Women Voters, local chambers of commerce, and college audiences in Pennsylvania. Members of the Commission also made media appearances and contributed opinion editorials to newspapers, prepared news releases and provided background information to the media. The Commission compiled complete research data on women by collecting statistics on women in the family, labor force, education, and other categories. The PACW published a quarterly newsletter Women's News, which provided information on legislation and other data and events of particular concern to women. They also published pamphlets and brochures on topics such as sexual harassment, day care options, and divorce. Each brochure and pamphlet advised women of their legal rights and provided a list of state services, programs, and agencies to assist them.
The Commission participated in and worked closely with associations and coalitions of women's groups throughout Pennsylvania and the Mid-Atlantic region. In this capacity, they provided information and training for local organizations in a statewide conference for local commissions for women.
The PACW also founded More Women Candidates, a non-partisan organization which developed educational programs to increase the number of women candidates for public office. In this capacity, the Commission also committed to a ten-year project from 1981 to 1991 in order to track the number of women in elected office. The project collected, reported, and publicized the number of women elected to public office at all levels of government.
The Pennsylvania Commission for Women continues its mission as an agent of change and empowerment for the Commonwealth's women. It has also expanded its scope and is an ardent advocate for health care, business, and human rights legislation concerning women. Governor Edward G. Rendell signed the most recent Executive Order to continue the PACW's work on June 22, 2003. Governor Rendell appointed twenty-six members to the Commission and named Leslie Stiles as Executive Director.
Cited: Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, Governor's Office, Executive Order 1975-3. Establishment of the Pennsylvania Commission for Women, February 27, 1975.
Pennsylvania Commission for Women Web site
Scope and Content Notes
The Pennsylvania Commission for Women Records date from 1979 to 1988 and document the activities of the organization to help insure women had full and equal rights as citizens of Pennsylvania and to advocate for the rights of women in the Commonwealth. Most of the documents in this collection were created during the tenure of PACW Director, Christine Myers Crist (1983-1987). Included in the records are meeting minutes, budget information, activities reports, publications, and workshop materials that illustrate the ways the PACW sought to accomplish their objective.
Previous Citation
Pennsylvania Commission for Women Records, 1979-1988, AIS.2006.06, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Arrangement
Series I. Administrative, 1980-1988
Series II. Education and Outreach, 1980-1987
Series III. Commission Publications, 1979-1987
Women; Women -- Pennsylvania; Divorce -- Pennsylvania; Credit -- Pennsylvania; Insurance -- Pennsylvania; Women's rights -- Pennsylvania; Sexual harassment of women -- Pennsylvania; Sex discrimination against women -- Pennsylvania; Social action; Government; Crist, Christine Myers; Pennsylvania. Commission for Women
- Administrative, 1980-1988; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains documents relating to the administration of the Pennsylvania Commission for Women (PACW) from 1980 to 1988. The majority of these files are meeting minutes, agendas, notes, and related information. These meetings set the tone for goals the commission sought to achieve. Information on such issues as child care and credit equality can be found in the files related to meetings. Most meetings were held quarterly in Harrisburg, unless noted. Included in this series are bi-weekly activities reports, research files on various women's issues, and budget reports submitted to the legislature, which provide a detailed summary of activities, progress made, and goals achieved. The Administrative series also contains files from More Women Candidates, a non-partisan organization founded by the commission to create educational programs to increase the number of women candidates for public office. This series is arranged chronologically.
  - PACW Meeting, December 17, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - PACW Meeting, April 29, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - PACW Director, Helen Seager Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - More Women Candidates Project, March 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - PACW Joint Meeting with Local Commissions for Women in Philadelphia, May 6, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - PACW Meeting, December 9, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence received by Christine Myers Crist, 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - PACW Bi-Weekly Reports, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Women in Government Research Files, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - PACW Bi-Weekly Reports, January-June, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - PACW Bi-Weekly Reports, July-December, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - PACW Executive Board Meeting, September 11, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - PACW Meeting, October 3, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - PACW Meeting on Day Care Needs in Pennsylvania, October 19, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - More Women Candidates, Project History and Meeting, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - PACW with Governor Dick Thornburgh Photograph, January 1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - PACW Meeting in Allentown, January 29, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - PACW Meeting, March 25, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - PACW Meeting in State College, June 5, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - PACW Meeting, October 28, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Senate Appropriation Committee regarding PACW Budget, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Auto Insurance Rates for Women Research, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence and Memos sent by Christine Myers Crist, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - National Women's Political Caucus ranking of Pennsylvania Appointed Cabinet Officers, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - State Government Transition Document regarding PACW, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Budget Review Meeting and Remarks given by Christine Myers Crist, January 10, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - PACW Meeting, January 29, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - PACW Meeting in Pittsburgh, June 11, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - PACW Meeting, September 10, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - PACW Meeting, November 14, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - PACW Orientation Meeting, November 14-15, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - First Pennsylvania Conference of Local Commissions for Women, November 15, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence Regarding New PACW Design, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - More Women Candidate Executive Board Meeting, December 5, 1986, January 7, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - More Women Candidates Meeting, March 10, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - More Women Candidates Meeting, March 10, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - More Women Candidates Information, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Budget Appropriation Justification, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - PACW Fact Sheet, Meeting Agenda, and Legislation of Interest, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - PACW Director, Christine Myers Crist Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Christine Myers Crist Biography, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Credit Rights of Women Research, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Education and Outreach, 1980-1987; II.
  The Education and Outreach series chronicles efforts to raise awareness and educate the public on various issues concerning women. The PACW was active in arranging programs, conferences, and workshops that dealt with a variety of issues relevant to women such as, re-entering the workforce, sexual discrimination and harassment, mental health, divorce, women in the workplace, and day care. Included in this series are files that were maintained by commission Director Christine Myers Crist on speaking engagements, and opinion-editorial pieces (Op-Eds) she wrote and newspaper clippings that cite PACW and the topics they worked to address. The material in the Education and Outreach series dates from 1980 to 1987 and is arranged chronologically.
  - PACW Events Newspaper clippings, 1980-1982, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Region III Conference of Commission for Women, November 19, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Families and Work Panel, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - More Women Candidates Caucus, January 1983 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Women, Poverty, and Public Policy Conference, October 28-29, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Region III Conference of Commission for Women, November 11-12, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - "Equality of the Sexes Still Evolving." Op-Ed by Christine Myers Crist for The Patriot (Harrisburg), June 5, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Pay Equity Newspaper clippings, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Women's Mental Health Steering Committee Report, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Christine Myers Crist's Pittsburgh Speaking Engagements, March 1985 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Women's History Week Speaker and Brownbag Lunch, March 5, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Christine Myers Crist's Johnstown Speaking Engagements, March 20, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Project Impact Workshop, March 27, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Daycare Interview and talking points, April 23, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Society of Consumer Affairs Professionals in Business Conference, April 28- May 1, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Region III Conference of Commissions for Women, may 10-11, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - We The Women 200 Women for Greater Philadelphia speaking engagement, May 28, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - National Association of Commissions for Women Conference, June 18-22, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Future of Women in the Workplace Workshop, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Symposium on Women's Issues, February 15-19, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Women's History Month Billboard Art Contest, March 1986 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Women's History Month materials and remarks by Christine Myers Crist, March 26, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Women's History Month Poster, March 26, 1986 (Box 1, Drawer 64)
  - Region III Conference of Commissions for Women, May 30-31, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Annual National Association of Commissions for Women Conference, June 18-21, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Partners for Pennsylvania Workshop, June 28, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - PACW Meeting with Ginny Thornburgh, August 26, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - "State Women Still Equality." Op-Ed by Christine Myers Crist for The Evening News (Harrisburg), August 26, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - League of Women Voters of the New Castle Area Speaking Engagement, September 1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Tri-County Women's Conference, October 11, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Almech Luncheon Speaking Engagement, October 27, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Pennsylvania Conference of Local Commissions for Women, November 15, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Women's Legislative Exchange Conference, March 10, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sexual Harassment in Housing and the Workplace, April 23, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Region III Conference of Commissions for Women, May 1-2, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Future of Women in the Workplace Conference Panel, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - PACW Issues Fact Sheets, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Commission Publications, 1979-1987; III.
  The Commission Publications series dates from 1979 to 1987 and is arranged chronologically by publication title. This series contains the Women's News, a statewide quarterly publication created by the PACW with information on topics that affected opportunities for women. The commission also created brochures and pamphlets detailing state services and programs available to women.
  - The Women's Report: A Commentary, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Women's News, September- October, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Women's News, May-August, November-December, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Women's News, January-February, May-June, November-December, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Women's News, January-December, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Women's News, January-December, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Women's News, January-December, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Women's News, January-October, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Women's News, January-December, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Women's News, Spring, Summer, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - PACW Annual Reports, 1980-1981, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - CETA Services to Women: A Program of the Pennsylvania Commission for Women, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - How it Works: The Pennsylvania Commission for Women, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous PACW Pamphlets, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Citizen's Guide to Block Grants, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - A Day Care Checklist, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Pennsylvania Divorce Law, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sexual Harassment on the Job, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Pennsylvania Commission for Women: Keeping Equality Alive, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - PACW Letterhead Folder and Christine Myers Crist Business Card, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)